<section id="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
<emphasis>KEDR framework</emphasis> provides the tools for runtime analysis (especially, verification) of kernel-mode drivers on Linux (<quote><phrase role="emphasized">KEDR</phrase></quote> is an acronym for <quote><phrase role="emphasized">KE</phrase>rnel-mode <phrase role="emphasized">D</phrase>rivers in <phrase role="emphasized">R</phrase>untime</quote>). The framework is intended to be used by the driver developers and may be useful for the driver certification systems as well.
</para>

<para>
The tools provided by KEDR operate on a driver chosen by the user (<firstterm>target driver</firstterm>). They monitor kernel function calls made by the driver, perform fault simulation, etc. This may complement many existing tools for error detection, fault simulation, memory checking, etc., that operate on the Linux kernel as a whole.
</para>

<para>
The typical usage of KEDR is essentially as follows. The user works with the target driver as usual or may be runs some specific tests on it. At the same time, KEDR tools are monitoring the operation of the driver, checking if it works correctly, doing fault simulation if requested, dumping the data about the actions made by the driver to some kind of a trace for future analysis, etc. 
</para>

<para>
KEDR framework is designed to be easy to extend and build upon. For example, the set of kernel functions to be monitored is fully customizable; fault simulation scenarios can also be provided and controlled by the user. Besides that, KEDR provides an interface to implement custom types of analysis via pluggable modules - in addition to call monitoring and fault simulation.
</para>

!!!TODO!!!: insert links to appropriate chapters
<!-- 
&nbsp;&mdash;
-->

<para>
Currently, KEDR works on x86 and x86-64 architectures. 
</para>

<para>
KEDR is free software and is distributed under the terms of <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/old-licenses/gpl-2.0.html">GNU General Public License Version 2</ulink>.
</para>

<para>
The latest stable version of KEDR as well as the development versions can be found at <ulink url="&kedr-url;"><quote>KEDR</quote> project site at BerliOS Developer.</ulink>
</para>

</section>
